Mazel טוב Mazel tov to today's דף, daf, it's ס"ג. Samech Gimmel.
Also remind everyone today or last night we started saying ותן טל
ומטר לברכה V'ten Tal U'matar Livracha in שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, December
5th, it's like the only הלכה halacha based on the English calendar.
Julian calendar. That and ניטל נאכט, Nittel Nacht, right. And the incorrect
English calendar, the Julian calendar. Okay. Anyway, let's start with the משנה
Mishnah on ס"ג. Samech Gimmel. לא יצא האיש לא בסייף, Lo yetzei
ha'ish lo besayif,
so we're back to what can and cannot be worn. And we
had a whole issue about what a man, a woman cannot wear
and that was a rabbinic problem, a man cannot wear that's a
rabbinic problem on שבת. Shabbos. Then what a woman cannot wear which
was a biblical issue, got into the whole issue about women wearing
a ring with a seal and the question about women's clothes as
opposed to men's clothes. And if something is clothing for one gender
is it considered carrying for the other gender. Now we go to
what a man cannot carry and that or cannot wear and if
he wears is considered biblical carrying on שבת. Shabbat. So let's take
a look. לא יצא האיש לא בסייף Lo yetzei ha'ish lo besayif
a man cannot go out with a sword. ולא בקשת V'lo bekeshet
or with a bow. ולא בתריס V'lo betris or with a shield.
ולא באלה V'lo be'alah an אלה alah which the גמרא Gemara will
explain is either some type of a spear or maybe a type
of a mace. ולא ברומח V'lo beromach רומח romach is a spear.
אם יצא Im yatza so you're wearing any of this type of
stuff, חייב חטאת Chayav chatat you're obligated a sin offering because that's
carrying, it's not wearing. רבי אליעזר אומר תכשיטין הן לו Rabbi Eliezer
omer tachshitin hein lo רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says they're תכשיטין, tachshitin,
they're a type of ornament, you know, people can dress up in
these military clothes, you know, they would have like what you know
like the like a royal military guard other people you know wear
a sword, you do these types of things as a particular way
of dressing up and of looking in a particular way. You're not
just using it because you're expecting to go to battle that day.
So it's an ornament, it's a nice way of dressing for certain
people.
Not שבתדיק Shabbos-dik kind of.
All right, well, that's maybe an issue. וחכמים אומרים אינם אלא לגנאי
V'chachamim omrim einam ela lignai no, I'm sorry, military clothing is not
something that looks ornamental and beautiful, they are really something that are
that is גנאי, gnai, not despicable, but how do they translate גנאי
gnai there? Reprehensible. Reprehensible, that's better. Reprehensible. שנאמר וכתתו, Shenemar v'chititu, so
it's not a positive symbol. Yes, it's symbolic. It's not all about
going to war, but it's not an acceptable symbol. It's not a
positive thing, the idea of this sort of military symbols. שנאמר וכתתו
חרבותם לאתים וחניתותיהם למזמרות Shenemar v'chititu charvotam l'ittim v'chanitoteihem l'mazmerot
they will grind their swords into plows and their swords into, what
is plowshares, spears into what is
it pruning shears, thank you, right, מזמרות, mazmerot, right, זומר, zomair, right,
pruning shears, I should have known it, it's the פסוק pasuk up
at the United Nations. ולא ישא גוי אל גוי חרב ולא ילמדו
עוד מלחמה V'lo yisa goy el goy cherev v'lo yilmedu od milchamah
one nation will not lift up against another nation a sword and
they will no longer learn war. Okay, therefore we don't want, we
don't like war. War is not an ideal, war is a very
negative phenomenon, and therefore we refuse to recognize these as תכשיטין. tachshitin.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to have a lot of a serious
discussion with this, it's quite fascinating that we bring in this sort
of messianic vision and we're bringing in like a value assessment about
how do we look at this, it's not just about societal norms.
But I do want to make the point, you know, that it's
not just a question of like is it aesthetically pleasing to be
called a תכשיטין? tachshitin? I mean we had before the idea of
the bandages that were worn, the קמיעות kameas that were worn, what
else did we talk about, oh the thing that was worn for
body odor, not...
תכשיטין tachshitin is not a category that is just about like aesthetically
nice. תכשיטין Tachshitin the way I've tried to explain it is something
that fundamentally is like considered connected to the body, being worn to
the body, not just that you're carrying it on your body. So
if you imagine, you know, that so a lot of this stuff
is interesting because you might be holding it in your hand like
a shield. But one imagines that a
sword, even if it's in its scabbard, right, and if you are
wearing that not because you're planning on needing it today but because
you know practically but because it looks nice, so would we really
say you're carrying it on your body? No. I mean if we
had to describe what you were doing we would say you're wearing
it. And you want it there because you want it on your
body because you like the way it looks and so on. So
what's interesting is that in an objective description it falls in the
category, should fall in the category of things being worn, not things
being carried. But before the, but because the Rabbis say we don't
approve of this, at least that's what the Rabbis argue on רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that this is appropriate as a way of looking
nice. It's appropriate to try to heal your wounds, to try to
look nice and have a brooch, to try to get rid of
your body or whatever, but it's not appropriate to try to look
nice with a sword on yourself and therefore we refuse to recognize
it as something that is being worn, as something that is like
connected to your body that you know has a right of being
sort of worn. So it's quite interesting the introduction of the values
as saying... Whether we're prepared to look at it as clothing or
not. You know, before as I said, we might have said this
is like we talked about רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir like a gold
tiara. So he said that that's also not being worn. Why? So
presumably it's because most people don't wear it. But even if that's
true, he's saying even though you're wearing it, most people don't. So
you're still going by the societal norms to define how do we
look at it. Here what חז"ל Chazal are doing is they're bringing
in sort of religious and value issues to say no matter how
it's treated in society, we refuse to recognize it as such. So
it's quite interesting I think, you know, that position. Let's just finish
the Mishnah or I'll finish the Mishnah as the comment. בירית טהורה,
Biryas tehorah, a בירית Biryas is tahor. We'll find some type of
a clasp for holding up like, you know, some stockings or various
like some type of a leg covering. ויוצאין בה בשבת, Veyotzin bah
BeShabbos, and you can go out on Shabbos because we're not afraid
you'll take it off. Why is it not tamei? Because it's not
directly clothing, it's holding other clothing. כבלים טמאים, Kivlayim tme'im, כבלים Kivlayim
are tamei, ואין יוצאין בהם בשבת Ve'ein yotzin bahem BeShabbos and you
cannot wear them on Shabbos and we'll discuss in the Gemara what
those are in contradistinction to the בירית. biryas. Okay. Like ropes. Or
they're like chains? Right. Chains, right. Like a slave. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
We'll discuss that in the Gemara. Yeah, go ahead.
So some say that it's chayav or some say it's assur?
No, חייב. chayav. Once because it's not a concern you'll take it
off. It's just we refuse to recognize it as clothing or as
a תכשיט. tachshit. So it's like a woman wearing a signet ring,
right? So I mean even though if she's personally wearing it because
it looks nice, but again the difference there is we could say
whatever you're doing society doesn't see this as a normal thing for
women to wear. But here that's not the it's not a societal
argument. Yes.
Does this get applied in modern times to automatic weapons and does
this get alluded to in the discussion of whether to draft yeshiva
students?
Well I don't know about the discussion of drafting yeshiva students. I
think that that argument is much more principled, and not I think,
I know, than about the details. You never want to argue the
details because then we could always work out the details. So anyway,
no, the issue about soldiers, you know, carrying their weapons on Shabbos,
you know, that definitely is addressed. Rav Goren has a whole book
about like Shabbos in the army and so on. I have to
check whether
he views it as an adornment.
Right. There is primarily the argument about just פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
But I do I was wondering the same whether this is ever
brought in but there the argument is fundamentally פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
Okay, one more quick comment and then we're going to go on.
Yeah, I mean, so if you're on base in the army then
you have to carry a gun on Shabbos because there was a
case where like there was a helicopter that came
in. Right.
So it's really a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh argument.
But there was a case where there was a shul outside of
the base on Shabbos and they called the rabbi and he said
you have to leave your gun on the base and go to
if you're going to go to shul that's outside the base.
Ah because there was he felt it wasn't a פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh situation.
So in that case it's פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and it's not
considered תכשיט.
tachshit. Interesting. Interesting. Okay, yes. All right, now let's take a look
at the Gemara. מאי בעלה, Mai ba'ala, what's an אלה? ala? So
קולפא. Kulpa. So what's קולפא? kulpa? So if you look at the
side it says
פירוש שבט שמכין בו וראשו עב, peirush shevet shemakin bo verosho av,
meaning a thick head. So thinking about a mace. Isn't that what
a mace is? What's a mace? Yes.
It's got a big ball at the end. But is that the
thing that's on a chain? No. No, that's something else. It's like
a big staff with a ball with spikes, right? So that's sort
of what I thought it was. All right, so let's keep it
going. Yeah, I think Steinsaltz has a hard time. What does he
identify it with?
He identifies it from a Persian source meaning club or a lance.
Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbi Eliezer omer, let's get now to the
debate. תכשיטין הן לו, tachshitin hen lo, these are ornaments. Says the
Gemara: תניא אמרו לו לרבי אליעזר, Tanya, amru lo leRebbi Eliezer, they
said to Rebbi Eliezer: וכי מאחר דתכשיטין הן לו, Vechi me'achar detachshitin
hen lo,
if you think that they're ornamental, מפני מה הן בטלים לעתיד לבוא
לימות המשיח, mipnei mah hen beteilim le'asid lavo lemot haMashiach,
why won't they be around? I mean why didn't it just say
there won't be war? But it's saying no, that they're actually going
to turn their swords into plowshares.
Well why? Where? Look nice! So why would you have to get
rid of it? Okay, so the answer could be it's a metaphor,
but no, let's see what he says, why aren't we going to
have it if it looks so nice? אמר להן, Amar lahen, he
said to them: לפי שאינן צריכין, Lefi she'einan tzrichin,
because they won't serve a purpose, שנאמר לא ישא גוי אל גוי
חרב. shenemar lo yisa goy el goy cherev. So therefore you know
they'll be yes ornamental but if they're meaningless then they won't serve
a purpose. So the Gemara says: ותהוי לנוי בעלמא, Vesehavei lenoy be'alma,
what do I care if they're serving a purpose? If they look
nice, they look nice! So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מידי דהוה אשרגא
בטיהרא, Midi dehavei ashraga betihara, like a candle in the midday. So
meaning if it's serving no purpose then it's seen as superfluous and
silly. So in a context in where there is no war, it's
not an ornament just because it's like a little bit of silver
on your back. It's an ornament in this particular cultural context in
which war is a relevant fact and ah you are like demonstrating
you know this like male attribute of valor and of courage and
of might, you know that's something that looks very nice on you
because of the symbols, not just because of the aesthetics. So in
a case in where that's not a reality and not a concern,
then it's. no longer carries that symbolism and is no longer you
know something that would be necessary. And not only necessary, therefore no
longer something that would be worn as an ornament. Yes, רב שי.
Reb Shai.
The משנה Mishnah already has the פסוק. Pasuk. Right? Why are they
going why are they...
So that's a very good point. The גמרא, Gemara, you see, if
you read the משנה Mishnah you would have said what they're saying
is they're not arguing like here it's you know in the גמרא
Gemara it's a much more technical argument. Like if they're really jewelry
so why won't they be worn לעתיד לבוא? L'atid Lavo? You know
it's not a value argument. It's like explain to me if it's
jewelry why aren't you wearing it later? You know the משנה Mishnah
is a much more value argument. The משנה Mishnah is from the
fact that we see that the prophecy is that there'll be a
time when there's no war, that tells us that symbols of war
are negative symbols and are non-accept and are not to be seen
as positive symbols and therefore not to be seen as acceptable symbols.
So the משנה Mishnah makes a much more stronger point. Right? The
גמרא Gemara is turning it into like a technical question. I know
you say they're not jewelry so why why if they're not jewelry
and you say they're jewelry
so why why won't you have this jewelry לעתיד לבוא? L'atid Lavo?
It's not making a value argument. It's just saying like why won't
you have it? He says, yeah because then there won't be any
purpose to it. Okay but you're right. The משנה Mishnah makes a
much stronger point. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this that
the so ופליגי דשמואל. U'pleigi d'Shmuel. This this meaning both according to
this version both the חכמים Chakhamim and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who
agree there won't be war in the future, the only question is
right now are they you know what type of a symbol are
they? Are they positive or negative? That argues on שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר
שמואל D'amur Shmuel because שמואל Shmuel says אין בין העולם הזה לימות
המשיח אלא שעבוד גלויות בלבד. Ein bein ha'olam hazeh limot Hamashiach ela
shibud galuyot bilvad. The only difference between now and Messianic time is
not war, it's not it's going to be a completely different world.
It's only going to be that we will have as the you
know the people of Israel will not be under foreign dominion they
will have self-rule and that's the basic difference between now and Messianic
times. Even if שמואל Shmuel is different than שעבוד מלכויות. Shibud malchuyot.
That's actually true. שעבוד גלויות Shibud galuyot means subject to right
exilic right you could have for foreign rules in the land of
Israel and that is true that in other variations of this it's
שעבוד מלכויות Shibud malchuyot and not שעבוד גלויות. Shibud galuyot. Very good
point. השנאמר Hashenemar as the פסוק Pasuk says כי לא יחדל אביון
מקרב הארץ. Ki lo yechdal evyon mikerev ha'aretz. The poor will never
cease from the land. Never. Even in Messianic times. So that means
it's not going to be a miraculous time. So you know not
economically and not in any way. It just means that we will
once again have מלכות. Malchus.
Even if we don't know how it was for פרנסה Parnassah it's
different.
Right. All right. מסייע ליה לרבי חייא בר אבא. Masiye lei l'Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba. This supports רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא כל הנביאים לא נתנבאו אלא לימות
המשיח. D'amur Rabbi Chiya bar Abba kol hanvi'im lo nitnabu ela limot
Hamashiach. All the prophets only prophesied you know for Messianic times meaning
all of the things about how things will be those are what
things will be in Messianic times. אבל לעולם הבא Aval l'olam haba
but for the future world עין לא ראתה אלהים זולתך. Ayin lo
ra'ata elokim zulatcha. God you know no eye has been has seen
this God other than you we can't even begin
to fathom what you know what it will be in Messianic times.
Okay so this is the מסייע ליה Masiye lei is I'm sorry
I might have said wrong it's not שמואל Shmuel who's מסייע ליה.
Masiye lei. This is actually the point that there won't be war
supports רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba because רבי חייא
בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said all of the prophecies are
for Messianic times. Meaning if שמואל Shmuel says that that Messianic times
everything will be normal pretty much, what does he do with all
of these miraculous prophecies? No war and you know the lamb and
the and the and the what is it? Wolf will lie down
together and all these types of things. What do you do with
that? What do you mean there'll be no? So no that's not
ימות המשיח Imot Hamashiach that's עולם הבא. Olam haba. Now it's important
to note that what does עולם הבא Olam haba mean? עולם הבא
Olam haba
for us often means like where your soul goes after it dies.
That's really has a lot to do with the רמב"ם Rambam who
redefined or who re-emphasized the concept of עולם הבא Olam haba as
the which this you know the world that you go to after
this world. In the גמרא Gemara עולם הבא Olam haba almost always
means the this world after the Messianic period. First משיח Mashiach comes
then there will be some
time of תחיית המתים Tchiyat hametim and then there will be the
עולם הבא Olam haba the world that follows the Messianic times. Okay
so yeah some type of a utopian world. So that's what so
שמואל Shmuel is saying the Messianic times it's not going to be
utopian. It's just be self-dominion. After the Messianic times all these prophecies
no war all of that that's עולם הבא. Olam haba. Okay whereas
here רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba is saying no
no no no. All of those prophecies is already Messianic times. That's
the utopia. What's עולם הבא? Olam haba? We can't even fathom what
עולם הבא Olam haba is. עין לא ראתה אלהים זולתך. Ayin lo
ra'ata elokim zulatcha. Okay so here's this interesting question about those different
stages. I want to read a little bit more and then I
have a number of comments to make.
They disagree, right?
Shmuel? Yes, שמואל Shmuel disagrees.
So the מסייע Masiye you said according to that is going on
what? What? What's the מסייע Masiye about?
מסייע Masiye is going on the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah that
assumes that there's no war in Messianic times is consistent with this
opinion. There's no war, that all of the prophecies are for messianic
times, not for עולם הבא. Olam Haba. Now the גמרא Gemara has
another version of this. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say, אמרו לו
לרבי אליעזר, amru lo l'Rabbi Eliezer, they said to Rabbi Eliezer: וכי
מאחר דתכשיטין הן לו מפני מה הן בטלין לימות
המשיח? vechi me'achar detachshitin hen lo mipnei ma hen betelin limot hamashiach?
So if they're ornaments, so why won't they be worn in messianic
times when there will be no war? אמר להם: amar lahem: אף
לימות המשיח אינן
בטלין. af limot hamashiach einan betelin. Who said? I'll say they will
be worn in messianic times. And what do you mean? What about
the פסוק pasuk about beating the swords into plowshares? No, that's עולם
הבא, Olam Haba, that's not messianic times. And I'm with שמואל, Shmuel,
just like שמואל Shmuel who says that messianic times things are more
or less going to be the same, there will be war. Okay?
So it will be in messianic times. ופליגא דרבי חייא בר אבא,
u'pleiga d'Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, it argued on רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba who says that no, in messianic times, that
will be, that's the utopia. עולם הבא Olam Haba is even beyond
that. Now I want to make a couple of comments about this
and in general and then its relevance to the שבת Shabbat discussion.
In general, this idea about whether משיח Mashiach will be messianic times
will be, you know, will be profoundly different, רמב"ם Rambam very much
emphasized the position of שמואל Shmuel even to the point where he
slightly misstated who was the majority opinion and who was the minority
opinion because if you look if you look slightly if you look
in משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, אמרו חכמים אין בין עולם הזה לימות
המשיח אלא שעבוד מלכויות בלבד amru chachamim ein bein olam hazeh liyemot
hamashiach ela shibud malchuyot bilvad like as if שמואל Shmuel were the
consensus and there were some other small opinions that said that משיח
Mashiach times will be you know utopian. So he sort of reversed
who was the minority and who was the majority opinion. It was
important for רמב"ם Rambam to do this because if you read things
that the רמב"ם Rambam wrote in פירוש המשניות Peirush HaMishnayot and elsewhere,
he was very upset, disturbed by the fact about how people would
obsess about the messianic times. I mean it's a good thing he
did not live in the Lubavitch era. But anyway, you know, he
says everybody wants to know what's going to happen in תחיית המתים,
techiyat hameitim, you know, if I die and I'm sick do I,
you know, and I'm missing a leg, then when I rise up
am I also missing a leg? And do I come up with
my clothes? Is it also going to be, you know, what exactly?
So he says and everybody was obsessed with that which is complete
nonsense. His basic point is you know what? We'll worry about it
when it happens. Okay? And רמב"ם's Rambam real emphasis anyway was about
the world of מצוות mitzvot is about is about creating a greater,
more just society, you know, not about some getting brownie points for
עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So he really wanted to sort of push
this focus away and therefore in other reasons as well, he underscored
שמואל's Shmuel position that even messianic times is going to be pretty
much the same. In a fascinating article that Dr. David Berger wrote,
he pointed out that ironically because the רמב"ם Rambam embraced שמואל's Shmuel
position and said oh no there's no big difference messianic times, that
actually gave support to messianic movements because if somebody comes along and
claims they're the משיח, Mashiach, the normal response would be well the
world looks pretty much the same as it did before. And oh,
but the רמב"ם Rambam said the world can look the same, so
I don't need to make the world different. So he says
the שבתי צבי, Shabbetai Zvi, you know נתן, Natan, you know his
sort of prophet or whatever, they used the רמב"ם Rambam to support
the idea that שבתי צבי Shabbetai Zvi was the משיח. Mashiach. He
says you know the religious Zionists use the idea that now is
messianic times, you know, or the beginning of messianic times. חב"ד Chabad
uses this about the רבי. Rebbe. So the fact that we're saying
it's not miraculous makes it easier to claim that a certain person
or a certain time is messianic times. So that's quite fascinating about
the ironic sort of result of embracing שמואל's Shmuel position. Anyway, so
that's one point about just that issue, that debate. The other question
in terms of the issue here the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim is interesting. You know as Rivka points
out the גמרא Gemara makes it a more technical question, well so
what are you doing you know well obviously it's not תכשיטין, tachshitin,
why would you be wearing it and so on. But you know
there's there could be more, you know, it seems in the משנה
Mishna that there's more than just the technical issue that's at stake.
First of all it's worth noting that is the reference to messianic
times just a reference to like trying to prove whether we see
this as a positive symbol or we see this as תכשיט? tachshit?
Or maybe you know a number of commentators have said that שבת
Shabbat is seen as מעין עולם הבא. me'ein Olam Haba. Now so
to what degree maybe we might want to be saying can we
if something is so, so you know antithetical to an idea of
an עולם הבא Olam Haba and so on then to what degree
can we be embracing it and accepting it as a norm and
accepting it as a type of appropriate clothing in the context of
שבת? Shabbat? So that's interesting to think about. Does this at all
have to do with a sense of שבת Shabbat as a type
of a מעין עולם הבא? me'ein Olam Haba? What's interesting though is
that the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between ימות המשיח Yemot HaMashiach and עולם
הבא. Olam Haba. Like it says I could concede עולם הבא Olam
Haba but ימות המשיח Yemot HaMashiach it will all be the same,
you know, so we don't say שבת Shabbat is מעין ימות המשיח.
me'ein Yemot HaMashiach. We say שבת Shabbat is מעין עולם הבא. me'ein
Olam Haba. Anyways that's one point. But I think the other issue
here really... is as I said, this question of using
how much, A, the use of values as opposed to societal norms
in determining whether we acknowledge this as acceptable clothing or
not, for example, like the גמרא Gemara never said that if somebody
wears something particularly provocative, you know, and revealing or whatever, oh, that's
not appropriate clothing, so that's what... you know, so it's interesting, just
the use of value, religious value statements to identify it. But what's
also interesting is the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
חכמים Chachamim about how do we sort of, you know, deal with
the here and now. Meaning, yes, in some ideal world, it's pacifistic
and there's no war and all of this, but the reality is
in this world, nobody's saying war's a good thing, but in this
world where war's part of our existence, you know, sort of maybe
signs of valor, of courage, of might, maybe these are genuinely positive
symbols and maybe we should even acknowledge them as positive symbols in
this world. Not that we're making some statement of some future ideal,
but in the realities of this world, this is... now you could
say, no, you know, that's מעשה ידי עשו, Ma'aseh Yedei Esav, it's
not positive symbols for Jews even in this world. But I think
it's an interesting... that's not what the Rabbis say. Their proof is
that in the future, it's not going to be. And רבי אליעזר'ס
Rabbi Eliezer's response might be, it's not spelled out, but might be,
yeah, but in this world we still have war and these still
are, you know, positive symbols in this world. So, I think that
that's interesting just to reflect on whether A, we use values to
determine what's appropriate clothing, not appropriate, or what's sort of defined as
clothing, and B, whether we... how do we look at these symbols
and to what degree do we look at them as positive symbols
or as negative symbols, and you know, and then how much do
we bring in certain types of future visions in order to assess
how we look at these symbols in the here and now. Charlie?
Okay, yeah, go ahead.
There were Jews who served in the Roman incursion armies, maybe רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is trying to be מיקל... meikel...
that's interesting. You don't get that sense, but that's interesting. Yes.
But so you're saying that despite that שבת Shabbat may be seen
as מעין עולם הבא, Me'ein Olam Ha-Ba, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
doesn't really... I guess, I don't... isn't really care so much to
apply that?
Yeah, I mean again, it's all very nice, it's all very nice
that some like, in some religious or some, you know, sort of
spiritual sense, but הלכה, Halacha, הלכה Halacha is this-worldly, and it's this-worldly
when you define also that what types of things are clothing or
not clothing, even if I concede that you use values in that
assessment. But if you want to argue to me that in the
here and now these are sort of seen as negative, we can
have that discussion, but don't tell me because of some utopian vision
that right now that translates this into, you know, negative symbols.
Is that a Kabbalistic kind of thing or is that actually mentioned
in the גמרא? Gemara?
No, that is in the גמרא, Gemara, but it's again, it's a
question of how much you use that in halachic discussion. Charlie, you
said your point. Okay, so let's continue now. Okay,
so where are we? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמר אביי לרב דימי, Amar Abaye l'Rav Dimi, אביי Abaye said to
רב דימי, Rav Dimi, רמי ליה לרבי אביא, Rami lei l'Rabbi Avya,
and some say he said to רבי אביא. Rabbi Avya. ואמרי ליה
רב יוסף לרב דימי, Ve-amre lei Rav Yosef l'Rav Dimi, and some
say it was רב יוסף Rav Yosef who said to רב דימי,
Rav Dimi, ואמרי ליה לרבי אביא, ve-amre lei l'Rabbi Avya, or maybe
it was to רבי אביא. Rabbi Avya. ואמרי ליה אביי לרב יוסף,
Ve-amre lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef, or maybe it was אביי Abaye who
said to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Anyway, someone said to someone: מאי
טעמא דרבי אליעזר? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? All right, you've sort of
explained the חכמים'ס Chachamim's point and how רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer answers
that whether it will be ornaments in the world to come or
in ימי משיח, Yimei Mashiach, but what's motivating his position? דאמר De-amar
so the רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר תכשיטין הן לו, De-amar tachshitin
hein lo, where does he get this idea that it is a
sort of acceptable or a positive symbol, not just a negative one?
דכתיב, De-chtiv, because the פסוק pasuk says: חגור חרבך על ירך גבור,
Chagur charbecha al yerech gibbor, gird your sword on your
thigh, oh hero, oh mighty one, הודך והדרך, hodecha ve-hadarecha, they are
your glory and your beauty. So it actually פסוק pasuk says that
when a valorous person is wearing his weapons, it makes him look
nice, it's his beauty, it's a
פסוק. pasuk. So you see that at least in this עולם הזה,
Olam Ha-Zeh, these things are... can be seen as positive symbols. אמר
ליה רב כהנא למר בריה דרב הונא, Amar lei Rav Kahana l'Mar
brei d'Rav Huna, or דרב עינא: d'Rav Ina: האי בדברי תורה כתיב.
Hai b'divrei Torah chtiv. No, that's not a proof. That's talking about
תורה. Torah. So you know that somehow, רש"י Rashi says what it
means is that you should like have your sword on your side,
you should constantly, you know, like have your, you know, have your
guns dry, and what is it, your
gunpowder dry, have your תורה Torah at ready to use it when
you have to, you know, it has to come to your defense
or to you know, you're not found with your, you know, with
your pants flat down or something, meaning have your sword on you,
have your תורה Torah on you. So that's what it's talking about.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה אין מקרא יוצא מידי פשוטו.
Amar lei ein mikra yotzei midei peshuto. Yeah, it's all very nice,
but there's still פשט. pshat. Okay, now if you just say there's
still פשט, pshat, which is just saying there's still פשט, pshat, and
you know, that doesn't totally change the פשט, pshat, but it could
also say there's no point in a... Therefore, even if it is
a metaphor, there's no point in a metaphor unless the image carries
weight. If it weren't true that wearing a sword would be seen
as something, you know, glorious for a warrior, then the metaphor would
be meaningless, even if it's meant as a metaphor. It's very interesting
to read the Artscroll
translation, quote-unquote, of שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim. Right? They directly read the
metaphor into the text. You know, there's no power to a metaphor
if it's not describing something out there in the real world. So
that's what he says. It's all very nice, it's a metaphor, but
it still is communicating a certain value. And it's still אין מקרא
יוצא מידי פשוטו. ein mikra yotzei midei peshuto. אמר רב כהנא, Amar
Rav Kahana, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said, כד הוינא בר תמני
סרי שנין, kad havina bar tamnei srei shanin, when I was eighteen
years old, והוה גמירנא ליה לכוליה הש"ס, vehavah gmirna leh lechulei haShas,
and I knew all of ש"ס. Shas. He didn't mean the בבלי,
Bavli, he meant all of ששה סדרי משנה. shisha sidrei mishna. Okay,
but anyway, but all of, but he did mean all of תורה
שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al peh. I knew it all by eighteen already.
ברם ולא הוה ידענא, beram velo havah yadana, I didn't know דאין
מקרא יוצא מידי פשוטו, de-ein mikra yotzei midei peshuto, that you can,
that, you know, that even after you, because it makes sense that
I knew all of ש"ס. Shas. There's a lot of ישיבה yeshiva
guys that are like this. You know, you are so much cold
about how the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh reading is the
halakhic meaning of the פסוק pasuk and how we have to accept
that that's what the פסוק pasuk is telling us, you know, על
פי הלכה, al pi halakhah, that you tend to say, and then
it can't mean anything else. And so he says, and that's what
I used to think, that there's no other legitimate reading other than
that. So עד השתא, ad hashta, and I didn't realize that until
now. So מאי קמ"ל, mai ka mashma lan, so okay, that's a
very nice little personal sharing, but what's the point of telling us
that? So דליגמור איניש והדר ליסבר, deligmar inish vehadar lisbor, to tell
us that it's possible to know all of ש"ס Shas without totally
having understood everything fully. And this is telling you an important principle
in learning. You know, maybe you should say you should have done
it better, you should have done it different, but the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara is saying actually that's an important
principle. First learn all the material, and then you could start analyzing
it and thinking about it. So he knew all of ש"ס Shas
and then he started realizing things that he hadn't realized before, which
goes back to the old question, you know, בקיאות b'kiut or עיון,
iyun, you know, you can't, you know, you can't analyze things unless
you have information at your disposal. So how much do you first
gather all the information before you begin thinking about it and analyzing
it? But anyway this is אין מקרא יוצא מידי פשוטו ein mikra
yotzei midei peshuto and the point is that look, at least, you
know, you got פסוקים, psukim, at least in this world, this type
of thing can be seen as a, you
know, glorious positive symbol. Yes.
By רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, you should consider requiring all your ישיבה
yeshiva students to have learned, to have gone through a דף יומי
Daf Yomi cycle before...
I know, there are definitely ישיבות yeshivot that actually really adopt this
and do, you know, but of course it started at a young
age, start at the age of five, you know, first have spent,
I mean my, I have a nephew that goes to such ישיבה
yeshiva in ישראל. Yisrael. They spend a certain number of years going
through all of תנ"ך Tanakh and having them memorize all of תנ"ך,
Tanakh, then a couple number of years having them learn all of
משנה Mishna and memorize all of משנה. Mishna. You know, obviously there's
some, it's not just straight memorization, there's some understanding there, but not
like, the focus is on getting all the information, not on, and
then you worry about the עיון. iyun. So there are definitely some
approaches like this. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבי
ירמיה אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rabbi Yirmiya amar
Rabbi Elazar, שני תלמידי חכמים. shenei talmidei chachamim.
So since we talked about this as being a metaphor for תורה,
Torah, now we're going to continue in that theme. שני תלמידי חכמים
המחדדים זה לזה בהלכה, shenei talmidei chachamim ha-mechadedim zeh la-zeh be-halakhah,
two Torah sages or Torah students that sharpen one another in הלכה,
halakhah, meaning like, you know, because they argue back and forth, you
know, like when you rub one knife against the other, it gets
them sharper. So that's the image, you know, because you're sort of
rubbing against one another, each one is sharpening their understanding. הקדוש ברוך
הוא מצליח להם, Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu matzliach la-hem, God causes them to
be successful. שנאמר, Shene'emar, והדרך צלח, va-hadarkha tz'lach, and your
and in your glory you should be successful, you should succeed. Okay,
that's the continuation of the פסוק. pasuk. חגור חרבך על ירך גבור
הודך והדרך, chagor charbekha al yerekh gibor hodekha va-hadarkha, gird your sword
and in your glory you should succeed. So where do you get
the idea of sharpening? אל תקרי והדרך, al tikrei va-hadarkha,
don't read it "your glory" אלא וחדדך, ela ve-chadadkha,
your sharpening. So if you sharpen one another, you'll succeed. ולא עוד,
v'lo od, not only that,
אלא שעולים לגדולה, ela she-olim li-gdula, you you get to be a
great, in a great position. שנאמר, shene'emar, צלח רכב, tz'lach rekhav,
succeed and ride high. יכול אפילו שלא לשמה, yakhol afilu she-lo li-shmah,
maybe even if you're learning תורה Torah not for the right purpose,
you know, as a, as a way of succeeding but not for
the sake of proper proper religious purposes? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, על
דבר אמת. al devar emet. This is just reading the פסוק, pasuk,
like "go and, you know, succeed and ride high on the words
of truth." So if it's a truthful approach, that's when you'll succeed.
ואם הגיס דעתו, ve-im higis da'ato, if he becomes haughty because you're
being so
successful, יכול אם הגיס דעתו, yakhol im higis da'ato, maybe you continue
to be successful if you're haughty? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, וענוה צדק,
ve-anvah tzedek, and words of truth and of humbleness and of righteousness.
So only when it's with ענוה, anvah, with humbleness, is this the
case. ואם עושים כן, ve-im osim ken, and if you do this,
זוכים לתורה שניתנה בימין, zokhim le-Torah she-nitna be-yamin, you merit the Torah
that was given in God's right hand. שנאמר, shene'emar, ותורך נוראות ימינך,
ve-torkha nora'ot yaminekha, your right hand will teach you wonders. So that
means the תורה. Torah. that is given in the ימין yamin in
the right hand. רבי נחמן בר יצחק Rabbi Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר
amar דברי תורה כתיב divrei Torah ktiv right? Because it
says the end, right. So what we are doing, thank you for
pointing that out, what we are doing is we are taking up
the point that was said no, this whole thing is a metaphor
for Torah, and we are continuing to interpret the פסוקים psukim within
this Torah context. רבי נחמן בר יצחק אומר Rabbi Nachman bar Yitzchak
omer זוכין דברים שנאמרו בימינה של תורה. zochin dvarim shene'emru b'yemina shel
Torah. Not just the תורה Torah that was given in God's right
hand, but the right side of the תורה. Torah. What does this
mean? דאמר רבה בר רב שילא d'amar Rabbah bar Rav Shila ואמרי
לה אמר רב יוסף בר חמא אמר רב ששת v'amri lei amar
Rav Yosef bar Chama amar Rav Sheshet מאי דכתיב mai d'chtiv what's
meant by the פסוק pasuk אורך ימים בימינה בשמאלה עושר וכבוד orech
yamim b'yemina b'smola osher v'chavod long life in the right hand, in
the left hand wealth and honor. אלא בימינה אורך ימים איכא עושר
וכבוד ליכא? ela b'yemina orech yamim ika osher v'chavod lika? So what,
on the right hand you only get long life, you don't also
get wealth and honor? So that's impossible. I mean, first of all,
it's the right, which is obviously the better. And second of all,
presumably, if you get long days, you should get everything that comes
with that. אלא הכי קאמר. ela hachi ka'amar. First of all, and
what is right and left mean anyway is also part of the
question. למיימינין בה l'mayminim bah those that
approach the תורה Torah on the right, so, you know, do it
the right way, the correct way, meaning but, you know, right being
correct, אורך ימים איכא وכל שכן עושר וכבוד. orech yamim ika v'chol
shekein osher v'chavod. First of all you get long
days, and of course if you get long days, you also get
wealth and glory. ולמשמאילין בה v'lam'smilin bah those that do it on
the left, we'll talk about what that means in a minute, עושר
וכבוד איכא אורך ימים ליכא. osher v'chavod ika orech yamim lika. Fine,
you'll get some glory, you'll get wealth, but אורך ימים orech yamim
like you're not going to get the אורך ימים. orech yamim. And
this guy, if you sharpen one another לשמה, lishma, you'll get the
right half of the תורה Torah which is both long days and
the wealth and glory. So what's משמאילים בה? masmili bah? רש"י Rashi
says שאין יגעים בה כל צרכן. she'ein yegiam bah kol tzarchan. That,
you know, you learn it, you're learning it לשמה, lishma, because if
you aren't learning it לשמה, lishma, why are you getting all of
this great reward? But you don't really, there's not too much self-sacrifice
that goes into the learning. אי נמי ee nami מיימינים בה עוסקים
לשמה משמאילים שלא לשמה. mayminim bah oskim lishma masmilin shelo lishma. And
then רש"י Rashi suggests no, maybe משמאילים masmilin even means שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma, which is quite interesting that שלא לשמה shelo lishma you
can get עושר וכבוד. osher v'chavod. But תוספות Tosafot talks about two
types of שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. We normally say you should always
learn תורה Torah שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה. shelo lishma
shemitoch shelo lishma ba lishma. And others, בא לשמה, ba lishma, and
the other גמרא Gemara says that anybody who learns תורה Torah שלא
לשמה, shelo lishma, you know, נעשית לו סם מיתה, na'asit lo sam
mita, מוטב לו שלא נברא. mutav lo shelo nivra. So תוספות Tosafot
basically says look, there's שלא לשמה shelo lishma which is that you're
doing it for like a, you know, for a like a really
like to attack תורה, Torah, you know, for things that are destructive
purposes, antithetical purposes. The normal שלא לשמה shelo lishma which we say
is a good thing because it'll lead to the right reasons is,
you know, not for antithetical purposes, but for the normal reasons we
do things. We have lots of motivations. Everybody else is doing it.
I'll look smart. I'll do this. I'll get a nice job. Whatever.
So that's not ideal, but it's not necessarily an antithetical. That we
say that מתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה mitoch shelo lishma ba lishma
and that also could be what one possible reading here even of
the עושר וכבוד. osher v'chavod. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רבי ירמיה... Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah... wait, זוכין דברים שנאמרו... no, not
here. אף על פי... אמר רבי ירמיה rabbi yirmeyah. אמר רבי שמעון
Amar Rabi Shimon, בן לקיש שני תלמידי חכמים הנוחים זה לזה בהלכה.
shnei talmidei chachamim hanochim zeh lazeh b'halacha. So before we talked about
sharpening one another, here we say two תורה Torah students who are
pleasant with one another, or רש"י Rashi says might mean lead one
another. You know, not like you argue with one another, you help
one another. It's a different type of a modality. הקדוש ברוך הוא
מקשיב להן. Hakadosh Baruch Hu makshiv lahen. God listens to them. שנאמר
shene'emar אז נדברו יראי השם. az nidberu yirei Hashem. Then those who
spoke, who feared God, spoke to one another, and says then God
listened. אין דיבור אלא נחת Ein dibur ela nachat and speaking means
the word דיבור dibur means either pleasantness or to lead. רש"י Rashi
has both explanations. שנאמר shene'emar ידבר עמים תחתינו. yadber amim tachteinu. He
will subjugate nations under us. So how does that mean it?
So if it means lead, then it means He will lead them
under us. If it means like pleasant, so it, you know, it
means like, you know, you like the same way you calm down,
you sort of like, you know, you make it settle. So here's
that sense of to make them underneath is to settle. It's a
harder read, which is why רש"י Rashi is inclined to say it
means to lead, not to be pleasant. Anyway, מהו ולחשבי שמו? mahu
u'lchoshvei shmo? The end of the פסוק pasuk is that those who
feared Him and those that consider His name. אמר רבי אמי Amar
Rabbi Ami אפילו חושב לעשות מצוה ונאנס ולא עשאה afilu choshev la'asot
mitzvah v'ne'enas v'lo asah מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו עשאה. ma'ala alav hakatuv
k'ilu asah. Even if you were intending to do a מצוה mitzvah
and something happened and you weren't able to, you still get credit.
Now that was parenthetical because that was just we quoted this פסוק,
pasuk, but we're really focusing on these metaphors for תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. So we're going to get back to that. אמר רבי חנינא
בר אידי Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Idi כל העושה מצוה כמאמרה kol
ha'oseh mitzvah k'ma'amarah אין מבשרים אותו בשורות רעות. ein mevasrim oto b'sorot
ra'ot. Anybody that does a מצוה mitzvah the right way, you do
not does not get, you know, bad report, you know, only only
hears good reports. שנאמר shene'emar the פסוק pasuk says שומר מצוה לא
ידע דבר רע. shomer mitzvah lo yeda davar ra. Somebody who keeps
a מצוה mitzvah will never know of anything bad. Like right, right?
Yeah, if you do it completely right, which is a good way
of dealing with all the times when people do know bad, hear
about things. Okay, so אמר רבי אסי ואיתימא רבי חנינא amar Rabbi
Assi v'itayma Rabbi Chanina אפילו הקדוש ברוך הוא גוזר גזירה הוא מבטלה.
afilu Hakadosh Baruch Hu gozer gzeira hu mevatla. Even if God... Even
if God makes a גזירה *gezerah*, if you are somebody that does
all the מצוות *mitzvos* and does everything right, you can nullify God's
גזירות *gezeros*. שנאמר Shene'emar, *shenemar*, באשר *ba'asher*, this earlier פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
in קהלת *Kohelet*, באשר דבר מלך שילטון *ba'asher devar melech shilton*, and
in the word of the king is שילטון *shilton* is authority, ומי
יאמר לו מה תעשה *u-mi yomar lo mah ta'aseh*, who can tell
the king what to do? וסמיך ליה *ve-samich leh*, and the next
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is שומר מצוה לא ידע דבר רע *shomer mitzvah
lo yeda davar ra*. So who can tell the king what to
do? A שומר מצוה *shomer mitzvah*. So if you're good at doing
the מצוות *mitzvos*, you can tell God, you can be גוזר ומקיים
*gozer u-mekayem*. I'm not going to unpack that one now. אמר רבי
אבא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Amar Rabi Abba Amar Rabi Shimon
ben Lakish, *Amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish*. Now that
was a digression about מצוות *mitzvos*, but back to תורה Torah *Torah*.
שני תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim. המקשיבים זה לזה בהלכה *Shene talmide chachamim
ha-makshivim zeh la-zeh be-halachah*. So we had sharpen, we had to listen,
or
I'm sorry we had to sharpen, we had to lead, and now
we're doing המקשיבים *ha-makshivim*, if you listen to one another. That's also
very important. One is you're leading the other person, the other is
no, you're actually listening. So if you listen to one another, הקדוש
ברוך הוא hu, שומע לקולם *Hakadosh Baruch Hu shome'a le-kolam*, God listens.
שנאמר Shene'emar, *shenemar*, היושבת בגנים *ha-yoshevet ba-ganim*, the one who dwells in
the gardens, חברים מקשיבים לקולך השמיעני *chaverim makshivim le-kolech hashmi'ini*. The friends
listen to your voice, listen to me, so there the friends when
they listen to their voice, God listens. ואם אין עושים כן *ve-im
en osim ken*, גורמים לשכינה שסתלק מישראל *gormim la-Shechinah she-tistalek mi-Yisrael*. If
not, the divine presence leaves Israel. שנאמר *shenemar*, ברח דודי ודמה לך
לצבי או o לעופר האילים *berach dodi u-demah le-cha litzvi o le-ofer
ha-ayalim*, my beloved one runs away. Now I want to make a
comment here because I think the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is doing something
very important because it started by the metaphor of the sword or
whatever as a metaphor for תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah *Talmud Torah*. And
we have that very often that the idea of the fight of
תורה *Torah*, מלחמתה של תורה *milchamtah shel Torah*, and the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* speaks about when you learn you נעשה שונאים זה לזה *na'aseh
son'im zeh la-zeh* and then afterwards then you become אוהבים זה לזה
*ohavim zeh la-zeh*. This very aggressive confrontational type of way. And what
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is doing is I think it's shifting it.
That right at the beginning it says to sharpen. Sharpen is not
to attack. Yes, it has some of that idea of the swords,
but still it's running the swords one against the other in order
to sharpen. So it's moving away from the direct aggressive attack
and even more than that the next things about leading one another,
listening to one
another, and I think what it's doing is it's also interesting what
it tells you is the reward. To some degree it's constrained by
the פסוקים *psukim* it's dealing with, but the reward of the more
aggressive approach is you become a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham. *talmid
chacham*. That's what the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* says and you get the
תורה שניתנה בימין *Torah she-nittnah be-yamin* etc. But it says the reward
here about leading one another, listening to one another
is God listens, the שכינה *Shechinah* is present, if you don't do
this the שכינה *Shechinah* departs, which is much more this
utopian peaceful image. The presence of God and the dwelling of the
שכינה *Shechinah* that's sort of עולם הבא olam haba *olam ha-ba* type
of a vision. So it's very interesting these two different visions of
תורה *Torah* competing with one another. The same way in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* you had the competition of is this idea of aggressiveness
and strength or
whatever this positive thing or this negative thing. All right, so now
let's see how the גמרא gemara *Gemara* continues with that. אמר רבי
אבא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש Amar Rabi Abba Amar Rabi Shimon
ben Lakish, *Amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish*, so says
Rabbi Abba in the name of Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, שני תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim המדגילים זה לזה בהלכה *shene talmide chachamim ha-madgilim zeh
la-zeh be-halachah*, if two תורה *Torah* students are מדגיל *madgil* each one
another in הלכה halachah, *halachah*. What does this mean? רש״י *Rashi* says
it means that there's no רבי *Rebbi* around but you still get
together and you try to help one another out even though you
don't exactly know what's going on. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says that it
actually explicitly means that you cause one another to make a mistake,
meaning not intentionally, but because you're trying to teach one another and
you're actually leading one another a little bit astray.
So let's see, I forget, to skip over
maybe, I'm not sure, I'd have to check, it's not תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* here, I'll have to double check. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says הקדוש ברוך הוא אוהבן *Hakadosh Baruch Hu ohavan*,
God loves them. So that's amazing, even if you make mistakes or
even if you don't have your רבי *Rebbi* teaching you, God still
loves you. שנאמר *shenemar* as the פסוק *pasuk* says ודגלו עלי אהבה
*ve-diglo alay ahavah*, and his banner over me was love. So רש״י
*Rashi* says it means to heap, to bring people together even if
there's no רבי *Rebbi*. אמר רבא והוא דידעי צורתא דשמעתא *Amar Rava
ve-hu di-yade tzurta di-shma'ta*. That's only if you have basically in the
פרשה *parsha*, you know the shape of the discussion. If you're completely
ignorant, it's not so worthwhile. If you basically know the shape of
the discussion and you're muddling your way through, that's a positive thing.
והוא דלית להו רבא במתא למיגמר מיניה *Ve-hu di-let le-hu rabba be-mata
le-migmar mineh*. It's also if there's no רבי *Rebbi* for you to
learn from. If you could learn from somebody who really knows and
you decide I'm doing it on my own, then you don't get
any credit for making the mistakes. But if you have no choices
and you somewhat know what you're doing, then even that is a
positive thing. And again notice the stark contrast with this to the
beginning. The beginning is you sharpen the swords, you become big תלמידי
חכמים *talmide chachamim*, it's so great. Here it says yeah, but if
you're talking about God's presence, God loving you, God being present or
whatever, even if you're making mistakes the idea is sort of this
much more peaceful type of an idea, bringing people together, working together
and so on, which is a very different image and maybe different
results than the first discussion. All right, so let's... So let's continue
in the גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי שמעון, so I'm sorry, skipped a
line. אמר רבי אבא Rabi Abba אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabi
Shimon ben Lakish,
so now because we had a statement of רבי אבא in the
name of רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rabi Shimon ben Lakish, we're going
to have a couple of aggadic statements in the same name, no
longer connected to the theme. גדול המלוה יותר מן עושה צדקה, Gadol
hamalveh yoteir min oseh tzedakah, he who lends money to somebody, it's
greater than giving them outright charity. ומטיל בכיס יותר מכולן, Umatil bekis
yoteir mikulun, and if you invest, help them get a job, invest
in their business, more than anything, that's the highest level. Why? רש"י
Rashi says because it more retains the person's dignity, you know, to
lend, to invest in their business rather than to give outright צדקה.
tzedakah. The other point could also be made, it also helps make
them more self-sufficient,
you know, so that's also another, you know, and the greatest צדקה
tzedakah you can give is to give someone a job.
אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, אם תלמיד חכם נוקם
ונוטר, Im talmid chacham nokeim venoteir, if a Torah sage, even if
he's like a terrible personality, he's very, you know,
jealous, not jealous, he takes, yeah, like he bears a grudge, he
takes revenge, nevertheless, if he's a Torah sage,
נושכהו כנחש, Nuchshehu benachash, he's as bad as a snake, הוא, חגרהו
על מתניך, Chagreiho al matnecha, still, notice the by the way the
bind him on your on your loins, it's again the image of
the sword. Okay, now maybe the point is, a sword can be
dangerous, can be used destructively, and maybe this is somebody who, yes,
it's not great that he has this personality, but there's still if
he's a sage, there's still a lot of תורה to learn from
him. But you know what also maybe I would say, try to
keep it in its scabbard. You know, so it's interesting this imagery,
it's bad, but it's also good, maybe again against this sort of
war and sword imagery, but still you should stick close to him.
אם עם הארץ הוא חסיד, Im am ha'aretz hu chasid, now on
the other hand, if you see that an ignorant person is righteous,
אל תדור בשכונתו, Al tadur bishchunato, stay far away, even though you
think why, what's so bad? But the point is, no, because you
know the righteousness of an ignorant person is not necessarily, might be
righteous in the sort of religious sense, but not necessarily about, you
know, accurate in terms of his practices and הלכה, because an ignorant
righteousness could still lead to errors in practice. That's at least the
way רש"י Rashi explains it. I'm just going to have to go,
hold the questions for now. אמר רב כהנא אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, Amar Rav Kahana amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish, ואמרי לה אמר
רב אסי אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש, V'amri lei amar Rav Assi
amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish, ואמרי לה אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי
שמעון בן לקיש, V'amri lei amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Shimon ben
Lakish, so whoever said in the name of רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
כל המגדל כלב רע בתוך ביתו מונע חסד מתוך ביתו, Kol megadel
kelev ra betoch beito monei'a chesed mitoch beito, ואיתי מונע רעה מתוך
ביתו. V'ayti monei'a r'ah mitoch beito. If you raise a rabid dog,
a bad dog in your house, you are withholding kindness from your
house because nobody wants to come and visit you and you don't
get to do הכנסת אורחים, hachnasat orchim, you don't get to feed
the poor. שנאמר, למס מרעהו חסד. Lamas merei'ehu chased. To
למס, lamas, holds back from your friend חסד. chesed. What's
למס? lamas? שכן בלשון יווני קורין לכלב למס. Shekein bilashon yivani korin
lakelev lamas. In Greek they call a dog למס, lamas, Steinsaltz has
no idea what that is. Okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, אף פורק ממנו יראת שמיים, Af poreik mimenu
yirat shamayim, you even, you know, cast off the yoke of heaven.
שנאמר, ויראת שדי יעזוב, Veyirat Shaddai ya'azov, and the fear of God
you will abandon. I mean if you're not welcoming people and, you
know, caring for people and maybe your, you know, your bad dog
rubs off on you and leads to you to have an aggressive
type of an attitude, so that also leads to this bad. Again,
although we're doing this because it's all in the name of ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, you might want to connect it back to this
also this issue of aggressiveness and the negatives associated with that aggressiveness.
ההיא איתתא דעללה לההוא ביתא למיפא, Hahu iteta de'ala lehu beisa lemifa,
so there was a woman that went into somebody's house to bake,
to use their oven, right? There was usually communal ovens or whatever,
not everybody had an oven. She went into somebody's house to bake
bread. נבח
בה כלבא, Navach bah kalba, and the dog barked at her and
really startled her and scared her, and it made her fearful. איעקר
ולדה, It'akeir vlada, and so she had a miscarriage as a result.
אמר לה מרי דביתא, Amar lah marei debeisa, all this happened like
at the moment, so the owner was like, he heard his dog
barking, he was coming downstairs or upstairs, and he said, לא תיחלי
דשקיל ניביה, Lo teichli d'shakul nibeih, don't worry, don't be afraid of
my dog, don't worry, he didn't know what had happened. He says,
you know, it's, you know, the fangs have been removed, ושקלינו טופריה,
V'shaklinu tufreih, I've had it declawed, so you have nothing to be
afraid for. אמרה ליה, Amerah lei, she said to him, שקול טיבותך
ושדי אחיזרי, Shkol tivusach v'shadi achizrei,
go take all of your kindness, your nice words and throw them
on the thorns. כבר נד ולד, Kvar nad vlad, the fetus has
already miscarried, so it's a little too late for you to be
telling me that. So as a very powerful illustration about what a
bad dog can do, even if it doesn't have a bite. And
again, you know, I would tie this into that aggressiveness, even like
the verbal aggressiveness can be very destructive. I think this is somewhat
tying into the more aggressive and militaristic imagery of תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah. from before, which still doesn't mean that it doesn't go on
a lot in ישיבות yeshivas and it still is very helpful in
sharpening you and making you a better תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So
I don't think it's like all one or the other, but I
think that's exactly the ongoing tension and in a way the עולם
הזה עולם הבא olam hazeh olam haba type of a tension. It
would be all nice if we lived in עולם הבא and we
could all just be so pleasant and wonderful to one another and
still become big תלמידי חכמים. You know, so I think that there
is exactly that tension being played out here within the תלמוד תורה.
talmud torah. אמר רב הונה. Amar Rav Huna.
מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv what's meant by the
פסוק שמח בחור בילדותך ויטיבך לבך בימי בחורותיך samach bachur beyaldutcha veyetivcha
libcha bimei bechurotecha rejoice oh young man in your youth and let
your heart be good to you in the days of your youth
והלך בדרכי לבך ובמראה עיניך veholech bedarchei libcha ubemarei eineicha go do
whatever your heart desires and what your eyes see ודע vda but
know כי על כל אלה יביאך האלקים במשפט ki al kol eleh
yeviecha ha'elokim bamishpat you're going to be judged by God for all
of this. So how do you what's the פסוק telling you to
go have a good time or not have a good time? So
it says עד כאן דברי יצר הרע ad kan divrei yetzer hara
until ודע vda it's all what the יצר הרע yetzer hara is
telling you saying like this is what your your יצר הרע yetzer
hara will tell you go enjoy yourself you know what is it
eat drink and be merry or you know go enjoy yourself. But
מכאן ואילך דברי יצר טוב mikan ve'eilach divrei yetzer tov ודע vda
יצר טוב yetzer tov ודע vda is what the יצר טוב yetzer
tov is telling you. Yeah you want to do that? Don't forget
you're all going to you're going to have to stand in judgment
before God. Not clear well it does end with a ריש לקיש
reish lakish and we'll see ריש לקיש אמר reish lakish amar and
we've been talking about ריש לקיש reish lakish and it ties into
the into the Torah theme עד כאן דברי תורה ad kan divrei
torah מכאן ואילך למעשים טובים. mikan ve'eilach lema'asim tovim. The first part
is talking about דברי תורה. divrei torah. What does it mean? Rejoice
in your learning of Torah. And then when it says God will
bring you in judgment it means that the Torah has to translate
into מעשים טובים. ma'asim tovim. It's not just the learning of Torah
but it's also whether it plays out in a way of creating
a greater just society and in your actions and so on. Then
again notice so Torah now is about being having joy in the
learning. Again a very different image than the clashing militaristic one. It's
about everything you desire having joy and so on but also and
it's not just about being a תלמיד חכם. It's also about you
know how it translates in the מעשים טובים. ma'asim tovim. And again
this more idea of we're all fighting in the בית מדרש beit
midrash and becoming big תלמידי חכמים that more so militaristic type of
a of an image doesn't you know is all about the Torah.
It's not about what you do and the good that you do
in this world. So again I think it's very powerful the way
those initial two competing visions play out in this discussion of תלמוד
תורה. All right now we get back to what you can wear
on Shabbos. So בירית טהורה. biris tehorah. So
this בירית biris this clasp is that holds up your leggings or
whatever is טהורה tehorah because it's not an ornament it's not clothing
it just holds up your clothes but you can wear it on
Shabbos because it's there to function for your clothes. So אמר רב
יהודה amar rav yehuda בירית זו אצעדה biris zu etzada a בירית
biris is a bracelet. מתיב רב יוסף metiv rav yosef רב יוסף
rav yosef asks בירית טהורה ויוצא בה בשבת. biris tehorah veyotzei bah
beshabbos. If it says the בירית biris is טהורה tehorah ואילו אצעדה
ve'ilu etzada if it were a bracelet טמאה היא temei'ah hi it's
טמאה. temei'ah. We know that from the stories of מדין midyan and
other places a bracelet is טמאה temei'ah so it can't be it's
a bracelet. And so the גמרא Gemara says no הכי קאמר hachi
ka'amar this is what it means בירית תחת אצעדה עומדת. biris tachat
etzada omedet. The בירית biris serves the purpose as Rashi reads in
on the legs it's sort of like the bracelet on the arm.
Now really not even really the same purpose but basically it's a
bracelet for the leg meaning it's some type of a thing to
hold up your stockings or to hold to hold up your pants
legs. So that's why he describes it as a bracelet but it's
not a bracelet it's some ring around your leg. Okay and that's
why and I said why it's טהורה tehorah because it's not directly
a piece of clothing or an ornament. So יתיב רבין ורב הונא
קמיה דרבי ירמיה. yativ ravin verav huna kumei derabbi yirmeyah. So רבין
ravin and רב הונא rav huna were sitting in front of רבי
ירמיה. rabbi yirmeyah ויתיב רבי ירמיה וקא מנמנם veyativ rabbi yirmeyah veka
mnamnem and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah who was the Rebbe was dozing
off. So the students were sitting there and talking. ויתיב רבין וקאמר.
veyativ ravin veka'amar. So רבין ravin was sitting he's saying בירית באחת
biris be'achat בירית biris is one כבלים בשתים kevalim beshtayim כבלים kevalim
are two and that's why כבלים kevalim are טמאין. temei'in. Now why
just because they're two are they טמאין? temei'in? So maybe you have
one on each leg. So it's not so clear in Rashi, Tosafos
says something also not so clear but basically somehow if you have
two then maybe it's more done to double it up as a
type of an ornament and we're again afraid you might come to
take it off and show and so on and it's not it's
not just functional. Yeah I guess. Anyway the גמרא Gemara will now
rediscover let's see that's the initial way of reading it. אמר ליה
רב הונא. amar leih rav huna. So רב הונא rav huna said
back no אלו ואלו בשתים elu ve'elu beshtayim both the both the
בירית biris and the כבלים kevalim are two meaning one on each
leg presumably. But what is the כבלים? kevalim? Here's what the כבלים
kevalim is as Michael said כבלים kevalim are chains.
ומטיל שלשלת ביניהם. umatil shalshelet beineihem. The כבלים kevalim is that you
actually have some type of a chain between the two of between
the two like rings you know that are that are running between
your legs ונעשו כבלים venasu kevalim
and that turns it into a כבלים. kevalim. So now so that's
the כבלים. kevalim. It's these leggings these bracelets braces on the legs
which are connected by a chain. So first of all like why
is somebody doing that? So well let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara says. ושלשלת שבו משוי ליה מנא? veshalshelet shebo mashavei leih
mana? I don't get it says the גמרא. Gemara The chain turns
it into a vessel? Why does the chain make it more of
a vessel to become טמא? tamei? Why does it make it more
of a problem on Shabbos?
So the
גמרא says וכי תימא כרבי שמואל בר נחמני vechi teima k'rabbi shmuel
bar nachmani maybe it's like רבי שמואל בר נחמני. rabbi shmuel bar
nachmani. דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן. de'amar rabbi shmuel
bar nachmani amar rabbi yochanan. You said in the name of רבי
יוחנן rabbi yochanan you might remember this מנין למשמיע קול בכלי מתכות
שהוא טמא? minayin lemashmia kol bichli matchot shehu tamei? So maybe here
too, not that it makes sound, but you know, it's metal, it's
who knows, somehow we'll call it a vessel because it's, because it's,
you know, because it's I don't know why, but that's what the
גמרא is going to say, maybe it did make some sound. But
anyway, here's what the גמרא says. One minute, גמרא says, בשלמא התם
קבעי ליה לקלא וקעביד מעשה. bishlama hatam kabailei lekola v'kaavid maaseh. No,
a musical instrument I understand, you know, you want the noise that
it makes and you're doing something with it, you're playing it, so
it doesn't have to be clothing to be טמא, tamei, even something
that's doing something like music. But here, הכא מאי מעשה קעביד? hacha
mai maaseh kaavid? What are you using it for? What are you
doing? How do you call it a כלי? kli? It's just this
chain. So הכא נמי hacha nami גמרא says קעביד מעשה. kaavid maaseh.
No, here too you're using it. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan,
משפחה אחת היתה בירושלים, mishpacha achat hayeta b'yerushalayim, there was a certain
family שהיו פסיעותיהן גסות shehayu pisioteihen gasot that had too wide of
steps and you know, they would take their, when they would walk
their stride would be too wide והיו בתולותיהן נושרות vehayu betuloteihen noshrot
and the young girls would lose their, would lose their hymen because
they would be, you know, they would take too, they would walk
with too wide steps. I don't know if that's possible. I mean
I know that too much like, you can be certain like gymnastics
and other types of things that might cause the hymen to rupture,
I'm not sure just by wide steps, but anyway, that's what it
says, that's at least what they believed. עשו להם כבליים, asu lahem
kavalayim, so what did they do? They wanted to have them take
narrower steps, so they made these types of chains that connected the
two legs, so they made the bracelets around the leg והטילו שרשרת
ביניהם vehetilu sharsheret beineihem and they put a chain between them שלא
יהיו פסיעותיהן גסות shelo yehu pisioteihen gasot so they wouldn't take too
big steps ולא יהיו בתולותיהן נושרות velo yehu betuloteihen noshrot and so
that their hymens would not, would not rupture. So presumably though that
then became some practice. Now the funny thing is that you might
imagine it with women, right, you might imagine it with women, I
mean different times society has, whether the men have done it or
the women have done it, but adopted very restrictive types of things,
you know, for, you know, that women would wear, like what are
those types of things that they had? Not the chastity belts. Something
that pulled the gut, corsets or something, right. So women in
chains?
Right, but the interesting thing is as Michael says, the story is
about women but the משנה is about men. So it seems like
at some stage this became a certain type of a thing to
wear for people that wanted to, I don't know, have smaller steps.
But it's all move on, no, no, no, we've moved on, we're
no longer military, we've moved on. So the גמרא says because somehow
it's used for taking for this purpose, it's considered a כלי. kli.
This is a type of thing you attach in order to adjust
your stride, it's a כלי kli and therefore it's טמא tamei and
presumably because it's not like your pants will fall down if you
take it off where you don't wear it on שבת, Shabbos, we're
afraid you'll take it off. So let's see the end of the
story. איתער בהו רבי ירמיה, itar behu Rabbi Yirmiyah, so this is
what the students were talking about when רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was
nodding off. Then רבי ירמיה woke up and אמר להו, amar lehu,
he said sometimes he wakes up and he says oh you got
it all wrong. Here he wakes up and he says יישר, יישר
כחך, yishar, yishar kochacha, good,
you know, you should be strengthened, that's the right explanation. וכן אמר
רבי יוחנן v'chen amar Rabbi Yochanan and that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says, that this thing is טמא tamei and it's a whatever
because it's a thing with a chain and it's used for controlling
steps. וכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, veki ata Rav Dimi
amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael he said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
מניין
לאריג כל שהוא שהוא טמא? minayin l'arig kol shehu shehu tamei? Now
we're getting back to טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah because we've been discussing
this thing is טמא tamei because it's used in a functional way,
now we're talking about other things that are טמא. tamei. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said how do you know that anything woven is
טמא, tamei, even a small size? מהציץ, mitzitz, from the ציץ. tzitz.
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said huh? וציץ
אריג הוא? vetzitz arig hu? The ציץ tzitz is woven? והתניא, vehatanya,
don't we learn in a ברייתא, Baraita, ציץ כמין טס של זהב,
tzitz kemin tas shel zahav, it was like a golden
plate ורוחבו שתי אצבעות, verochbo shtei etzbaot, it was two finger widths
wide ומוקף מאוזן לאוזן, umukkap me'ozen l'ozen, it ran from ear to
ear וכתב עליו בשתי שיטין, vekatav alav bishtei shitin, it was two
lines written on it. יוד ה"א למעלה, Yud Hei lemala, some say
יוד ה"א Yud Hei means the full G-d's name
וקודש למ"ד למטה vekadosh Lamed lemata and קודש לה' Kodesh Le underneath.
What, and others say is it doesn't mean that it's out of
order, it just means that it was like
he said you wanted G-d's name to be above but you still
want it to read it in order. So it was like קודש
לה' Kodesh Le and then it was you know
G-d's name was on a higher line but continuing in the right-left
reading. Okay, so anyway, but the point for us is that it's
a gold plate. ואמר רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אני ראיתיו ברומי, v'amar
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose ani raitiv b'Romi, I saw it in Rome,
which is you know
because Rome sacked the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and you know they
have Titus's Arch and whatever. So he said I saw it in
Rome. The interesting thing is that legends develop because the גמרא later
identifies Christianity with Rome, so legends develop that this means the Vatican
and all of the stuff of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is
in the Vatican. But that's not what he's saying. He said I
saw it. I saw it in Rome, and
the קודש לה׳ Kodesh LaHashem בשיטה אחת beshitah achat and it was
not on two lines, it was all on one line. It's very
funny, like okay, he has direct, he's giving a direct report of
what he saw, but he's still the minority opinion. Okay, anyway, כי
סליק רב דימי מנהרדעא שלחו להו. Ki silik Rav Dimi miNahardea shalchu
lehu. So when Rav Dimi came from Nahardea, so now we have
this question, what do you mean from the ציץ? tzitz? So Rav
Dimi said דברים שאמרתי לכם טעות הם בידי, devarim she'amarti lachem taut
hem beyadi,
what I originally told you was a mistake, it's not that he
said a little woven thing we learn from the ציץ. tzitz. ברם
כך אמרו משום רבי יוחנן, Beram kach amru mishum Rabbi Yochanan, here's
what they said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan. ומניין לתכשיט כלשהו
שהוא טמא, Uminayin letachshit kol shehu shehu tamei, how do you know
even a very small ornament is טמא, tamei, no matter what the
size is? מציץ, Mi'tzitz, from the ציץ. tzitz. Of course, I don't
know that a ציץ tzitz is a כלשהו, kol shehu, ציץ tzitz
is pretty big, but anyway, any ornament is טמא tamei even if
it's a small size. ומניין לאריג כלשהו שהוא טמא? Uminayin le'arig kol
shehu shehu tamei? How do you know even a small woven thing
is
טמא? tamei? מאו בגד. Me'o beged. It says or a clothing, so
the או o is describing things that become טמא, tamei, and the
או is considered to be broadening and inclusive, and therefore even something
very small. Now, I'm waiting for somebody, Michael, to ask me, maybe
he took me seriously when I said no questions, that before we
had like many דפים dappim that were discussing three fingers by three
fingers, three handbreadths by three handbreadths. Anyway, תוספות brings it in and
תוספות says that the difference is, that the basic difference is, is
that
if it was made initially,
I'm sorry, if it was made initially larger, then it would have
to be three by three in order to still be a בגד,
beged, because it's still just a remnant, it needs more significance in
terms of size. But if it was initially made to be a
garment, then no matter what the size is, that is its size.
So if you made initially some type of, I don't know,
a string garment, a tiny little thing, but that's how it's functioning,
even a tiny size is a garment. And let's just read one
more sentence on this line about this. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אריג
כלשהו טמא, arig kol shehu tamei, even a small woven thing is
טמא, tamei, even the smallest size,
ותכשיט כלשהו טמא, vetachshit kol shehu tamei, and even the smallest ornament
is טמא. tamei. אריג ותכשיט כלשהו טמא, Arig vetachshit kol shehu tamei,
if it's a combination woven and ornament, even a small size is
טמא. tamei. And we will pick up with this tomorrow as we
continue the discussion of טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah.